Lear Lambert. No, sir. The main intent of this bill is to improve school security at every school, both with hardened entrances requiring locked doors, having Homeland Security agents, one in each county, to evaluate that and work with local law enforcement. And then there is a budget that we will be considered in a few weeks that includes $140 million for SROs.
Now, if some of these safety protocols fail and a school is not compliant with them, like having their doors locked, then one of the requirements of the bill is if you're not locking your doors and do not have a secure perimeter in that school, then you would be required to have an SRO.
Now, what has been recently announced by the governor and the proposal will be in the budget is that those SROs will be paid for with state funds. In the original version of this, that would have been local funds.
So we're going to pay for that at the state level, making it much easier for every school to have an SRO. I will say that the intent is, is that every school would have at least one SRO, but it is not the main crux of this bill.
The main crux of this bill is a complete net over a school and a barrier surrounding that school so that the children inside are safe.
And to have a homeland security officer that's working with public and private schools to evaluate that safety, there's a variety of things that can happen.
For instance, um, there are some schools that have very large glass windows.
Um, there needs to be a plan in place on how to make sure if they look great in a school, but if they have a very, well, Mr. Speaker, I think he's motioning.
He doesn't want me to continue answering, but I'll stop and I don't want to take any of his time.
Please go ahead, sir.
All right.
Representative Pearson.
I just want to be able to ask a couple of follow-up questions here because of a couple of concerns, including the school to prison pipeline.
Is it a quick yes or no?
I know it's loud.
Do you know about the school to prison pipeline?
Lear Lambert.
Go ahead, sir, if you don't mind.
Representative Pearson.
Yep.
Uh, in schools, when we turn them into prisons, when we institutionalize them, the consequences and the effects disproportionately harm children, particularly children of color.
And I understand that after 14 years, uh, the chairman is bringing forward this legislation that you believe will actually make schools safer in the wake of very tragic incidences.
But I don't think that penalizing or advocating that our schools become more like prisons is the right solution.
The idea that I think we really should think about is how do we prevent people with assault rifles from going into schools?
And when you think about, when you think about the SROs who would be at these schools, are you saying that children will go to school and these resource officers will have AR-15s on them?
Or will they have handguns, uh, which compared to how many rounds an AR-15 could shoot and to kill people, uh, would be no match?
And this is a part of what I think is a symptomatic problem of really not addressing root causes.
The root cause that each of us have to address is this gun violence epidemic due to the proliferation of guns.
We don't need a solution that says, if you don't lock a door, get someone with a gun.
We need a solution that says people shouldn't be going to schools and to houses and to neighborhoods with weapons of war.
I would argue, I would argue, and I'm really curious, and I'll leave you with a few questions here toward the end.
And I appreciate what one of the representatives said, that we don't want gun battles at schoolhouses.
And what's deeply concerning is there's no clarification about what type of training people would get.
What happens when one of these school resource officers accidentally kills an innocent kid?
What happens when we have people who we have given the authority to actually harm our children,
to actually harm our teachers, this type of power?
It isn't having more contracts with gun owners, right, to be able to provide guns to school resource officers.
It's to prevent people who shouldn't have guns through red flag laws, through storage protection,
from ever getting access to our schools and communities.
Lear Lambert, you're recognized.
Thank you, Mr. Speaker.
And for those in the gallery, please don't drop stuff.
While Representative Pearson was speaking, someone almost hit him with a sign.
So please just, you're here, we want to hear from you, but please don't drop things on people.
So I just noticed as he was speaking, it almost got him there.
It's just a sign, but I don't want that to happen.
So to your speech, I will say this.
This doesn't create a prison for schools.
It creates a fortress.
A prison is designed to keep people in.
A fortress throughout all human history is designed to keep danger out and to keep those that are within safe.
This does create safety for our schools.
You may not like that that's necessary, but in this dangerous world that we live in,
it is obvious that we have to make sure that at least somewhere in this state,
there is a place that children can go and learn in peace and be safe.
It absolutely does help create a fortress around our children.
But it, it, I'm not sure if you understand the distinction between prison and fortress,
but I hope that helps because a prison keeps people in,
a fortress keeps people out and keeps people safe.
Thank you, Mr. Speaker.
Representative Fritz.
And, and to the sponsor, I just want to say thank you, um, for.
Thank you.